welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
with this it's gonna be a liminal
recording so at the end anybody in this
room who wants the veto the recording we
will delete it and destroy it if you
want your face shown just going to
off-camera but so we are gonna record it
with this unknowingness of what we're
gonna do with it if no one vetoes it
it's gonna get posted on YouTube
so Jared Jason one be like three of us
just check-ins before we kind of
introduce today like I can go first so
so calm I think that's all I got right
now I feel fine
well if you ever guys ever heard of that
just joking yeah I don't know kind of
playful actually it seems quite calm as
well so be fun I think the last one we
had here there's just like this subtle
background of putting a call for some
more conflict because because our last
hour less a mediation it seemed like
that was something people wanted to get
a little bit more friction or so you
kind of put ourselves at risk in some
ways so I can feel that kind of in the
background as well which is kind of
exciting and and yeah I'm feeling like I
want to play in that playground so cool
so welcome to the store I'm Peter
Lindberg the Stewart of the store and
the store as a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this moment and this
is I think our fourth mediation campfire
and Jason Jay and myself were talking
yesterday and it was like oh my gosh is
that all these delicious insights we're
coming up my gosh I wish we had that
recorded so what we're gonna do
today is that we're each going to take a
turn just kind of share our latest
thoughts on mimetic mediation and what
we see of this campfire
the whole project in general and then we
might go around to follow up thoughts
and then we'll throw it to the group for
a group discussion like the other times
I think that's everything so if you guys
are okay I can I can open with my my
thoughts cool no I took notes to do that
I wanted to be serious about this so one
thing that came up yesterday we were
talking is my memory of an actual
mediator so I used to work at the
University of Toronto and so and there
was like 21 different unions and the
union's you know they I had like
negotiations and collective agreements
with the University so they brought in a
mediated from the Ontario government and
this guy he was like slick he was like
hyper charming there's like sort of like
an amoral quality to him as well he just
wanted to sort of get a deal done he
didn't really have a side or a bias it
seemed like and I felt into that and I
kind of felt into this mimetic mediation
project and sort of like teased out
potential skills to stack or this is
sort of my provisional skill stack or
talent stack of a mimetic mediator or
maybe mindset might be a better
whatever you're looking at it there has
to be sort of like a trust
I felt sense of trust that kind of all
parties are involved they trust the
mediator to some to some capacity and
maybe like a minimal viable status you
know that some kind of like saying that
you know you want to reach out to this
mimetic mediator and when you're in the
process of mediation I I think there has
to be this sense that you genuinely have
to be in a liminal state of
unknowingness of not knowing who's right
and we were talking like there's a whole
kind of thing about both sides ISM or
all sides of zone like I don't think
there's a medium of like of like let's
say for example we have a friend Jessica
Burton she's a she's a feminist really
considered feminist she had a
conversation with some in so I was like
a woman hater or something like that
it's not like okay somewhere in between
their ideologies that's where we want to
be like no like that's not where we're
saying like
would obviously side with propositional
with Jessica but I think if some
arrangement like that happened I think
the goal or this is mikage of my
thinking the goal of a mediator is to
find right relationship between that
mimetic tribe or those two people or
whatever and that right relationship is
gonna be a different combination each
time and in order to encourage or
engender that right relationship it's
you got to find you have to have the
capacity to be in right relationship
with those individuals those mimetic
tribes and all the different sub
personalities within yourself that get
triggered when you experience radically
different perspectives and points of
views and then so the other thing I
would I would say is that it's almost
like a bait and switch in a way like
this and Jared was I think some good
pushback on the actual term mimetic
mediation was like is it really mimetic
mediation we're doing and I think in
order to be a good mimetic mediator or
have a sense of the culture war you have
to be able to dip away from the
proposition away from the memes and then
into the felt sense the actual kind of
like speak yeah capacity to speak from
your heart and actually feel what other
people feel when they think what they
think and if you can speak the language
of the felt sense and I think it's like
you can speak to people directly and
it's almost like a being switch you're
using when you're you're kind of you're
using the mimetic and the narratives and
all that type of stuff but you're really
speaking to them heart to heart so
that's the edge of my thinking and I
will
whoever if Jason Jared want to go next
feel free to jump in
you just won one points that maybe
slightly different this on the you said
Peter about kind of you know not going
as a if you're kind of playing this role
of a mediator whether more formal or
more informal not having not knowing
where it's gonna go I also think it's
important to for everybody to kind of
acknowledge their biases upfront to like
wear them on your sleeve because I think
I don't think anybody is without bias
and if you're a mediator and you're kind
of this kind of trusted third party this
neutral third party I think having you
know your bias out there like okay this
is you know I can express my
one of you you say hey look this is this
is what it is and I'm not gonna you know
I'm gonna try my best not to use that to
kind of tip the scales one more the
other but this is what it is and so
everybody else can see that as you know
when I'm doing my work as a mediator
like they'll you know they'll be in a
better position to notice when I'm
tipping the scales I guess right because
I'm not sneak you know it in a sneaky
way kind of like injecting my bias into
like how you know I might I don't know
ask a follow-up question from from you
know one person to the other and and you
know I mean it can be it can all get
very from my point of view can it can
get all get very I don't know cringy
real quick or it can get very can pull
apart real quick if that's just not not
out there
maybe maybe I'll give you a chance here
yeah so I guess kind of kind of uh
abstractly the way I kind of see
mediation is or mediation whatever we're
calling this it's really like simply
being able to see other people's
perspective not fully because it's
always because we have a kind of
difference reference point but to see
that we have to kind of remove or we
have to kind of see it from the outside
own perspective from the outside in and
attempted to see their own perspective
from outside in and so really like I
think the mediation is is what's
happening when the space in between the
ideas or the perspectives it's kind of
illuminated right like it's made yeah
this becomes a connective tissue it's
like the space in between is kind of
alive where everybody's looking there to
try and orient and understand each of
our each of the perspectives included
and to kind of pull in this like
we're framing our own cognitive biases
and and agendas and ideologies I think
that the best kind of framing there is
just to see simply that like when we're
mediating if we're the person in between
we're trying to illuminate that space
but we should still see our own kind of
emotional attachment to beliefs that are
arising as just another interlocutor
right so besides not removing ourselves
just from the two that are or it's a
group but we include ourselves our own
ideas and biases in that in that thing
and so to Jason's point that means kind
of airing it you know like maybe you
know as I think it would be a valuable
tool for the mediator to say you know
like hey I'm trying to be impartial here
but I also you know have a background of
my dad a lot of family here so it's it's
hard for me to completely go there or
something like that or I'm feeling some
sort of emotional resonance but this
also does point to a Jason's talked
about is like this is you know the same
types of mediation is happening we can
the same process can happen when we
interact with anybody and and the more
we practice it kind of being able to see
our own perspective from a distance the
more we're prepared to be able to help
in a group and and this does kind of
point to some of the more spiritual
elements of this too which is kind of
finding the interworkings of the
attachment to the ideas that arise and
the more that the looser we are attached
to those ideas the easier it is for them
to only offer themselves when the
context is right yeah that's just a what
you're saying is this is how I'm kind of
seeing it from my perspective and I
think what we were saying yesterday it's
like having that tension always
available where you acknowledge your
bias like what's your actual position or
you think your positions are with the
willingness to sacrifice time at the
moment's notice and if you can hold that
tension and other people to see it then
I think trust the felt sense of trust
will emerge from a wide variety of
different ideologies because there's
like a flirtatious element there you're
up for grabs all right it's like it's
almost like you get that nice edge of
being up for grabs for therefore their
ideology
I think you
have to be at that place in order to get
into real dialogue with them and so like
practically speaking but we were talking
there was like so much and the thing
we've said like we should calm down just
take it one one one session at a time
because there's so much potential with
this project and there's so much
different kind of like sessions that
could emerge from it or how much we
could do with these sessions and I think
previously you know Jordan Hall emailed
me with an idea about how they could
have like a news channel like I'm a
medic mimetic tribe news channel we're
like someone talks about you know social
justice activism I got like a situation
that happens in the world that that
affects people about Trump or covet or
whatever get the social justice take you
got the queuing on take you get sort of
like men's rights activist take you know
you get the dirt bag left whatever and
so we have like a news channel everyone
can kind of share their opinion I
thought that was pretty cool and I think
that's that's doable another thing we
mentioned so how I see the stoah space
emerging or evolving naturally is like
there's you know there's a wisdom gym a
section where people get to kind of like
practice their wisdom which is really
created by the collective intelligence
at this point there's like cyclic
technology incubators where people can
just test things things up and if
it works they could pour it into their
own the wisdom gym and then there's a
sort of like sense making sessions where
people come in these intellectuals who's
respected intellectuals come in and then
they share their thoughts and there's
Q&A and we've had many of those and some
of these are interesting because so we
had Alexander bard come in for example
and we had Dave Snowden and those two
they were on this listserv called
intellectual deep web they had like was
like cat and dogs they had a big fight
and then Dave Stoney just left that that
thing but now they're both getting
warmed by the campfire this though a
campfire they're trusting it and if they
become somewhat regulars maybe they can
have a conversation again in a good
faith way so next week Michael Brooks
from the Michael Brooks show he's coming
into stoah and Peter Burke OC and he
Peter just randomly texted me sometimes
he wants to talk and so I was kind of
you know synchronicity and I know they
don't like each other pas positionally
they could be warmed by the digital
campfire maybe we can connect them
so I kind of like the idea like these
people come in the campfire they feel
safe they feel warm they feel like you
know it was the trusted space they leave
then as meteors come in and say okay how
can we get these guys to talk to each
other maybe it's an anti debate maybe
it's an empathy circle what is the sort
of the angle or frame that would attract
them to discuss each other with each
other and then yeah yeah early over the
last thing another one is sort of like
Jared mentioned this is sort of like
there could be also sessions where you
just like method act a certain mimetic
tribe or a certain ideology feel what
they feel get really intimate with the
propositions that they use so you can
pass their ideological Turing test just
have at it and see what emerges
and if you can kind of like really feel
what they feel and an advocate for
strongly then maybe you can talk to them
better yeah I have a number of thoughts
and see if I can have them together so
so one going off of what you said Peter
with you know the mimetic mediators
being kind of the connective tissue you
know across these different
personalities you know somewhat
well-known personalities that are that
are coming into the stoah you know
getting comfortable with the platform
and trusting in the platform and then
you know us recognizing that hey like
there needs to be some you know dialog
between these people as well not just
having their own sessions and so you
know one use of these sessions is kind
of game planning you know how can we do
that but another one and I don't know if
this would be right away but actually
bringing say Michael Brooks and Bogosian
that would be interesting bringing them
in here with a bunch of us people you
know aspiring mediators of impact saying
and and helping to facilitate a
conversation and kind of providing the
guardrails if if one of us if it starts
getting heated but one of us realizes
hey will you actually might have
misunderstood where you've met there and
could you see it from this perspective
so just kind of like smoothing it out a
little bit that that's also a
possibility somewhat related I
I've been playing with these dual
notions of you know a lot of people when
talking about liminal space very liminal
time and we want to kind of encourage
this liminal space so we don't want to
have an agenda for where conversations
are gonna go by the same time this is
kind of counter concept to me is this
notion of generative tension we're out
of the liminal space you know you get
this kind of tension that arises and
hopefully it generates something you
know positive right so it's thinking you
know seeing as a mediator seeing tension
not as a problem but as an opportunity
for something to grow could I just
quickly ask a little bit on what the
mental space means to you what it means
to me is kind of a it's like a
transition period you know it's it's a
period where so a lot of people describe
kovin this close situations a liminal
time because before that you know a lot
of people kind of had you know an idea
about what was gonna happen and what
they were planning for what they're
preparing for and a liminal space kind
of when all of these kind of reference
points of you know how the world works
and where society is going or where our
lives are going kind of get thrown out
the window and it's just kind of this
kind of radical uncertainty or unknowing
that's my that's my take I don't know if
anybody else that has different take on
that but I mean so in relation to like
cultivating an intentional liminal space
it's it's more like okay we're having a
conversation and we have some ideas to
frame it to get it started but we don't
actually we're kind of operating in an
emotive uncertainty and so for example
like Jared I on our podcast we often
don't really plan our conversations like
we like it to just see what emerges you
know and it's and that's kind of scary
because like what if I don't have
something to talk about what if you know
I get nervous and I shut down or
something but you know but there's also
exciting because I don't know what's
gonna happen right and so something can
just come out that something really
delicious and interesting that all of a
sudden you know we can go
but it takes the ability to kind of
trust being in this liminal space in
this space of uncertainty of not knowing
so that's that's that's how I think
about it at least
I don't know if that was helpful or not
er I getting a feeling for it thank you
good let's see there anything else
generative tension and oh yeah so so
there's that so you know it's just
something I these two concepts I'm
playing in my mind of like liminal space
and generative tension and and and they
seem to be kind of this yin-yang
situation for me it seems like I think
about like what is well you know I want
to have the opposite of liminal space is
this kind of sense of certainty but
another but it seems like you think
about in terms of what can arise out of
them in space well all of a sudden these
polarities arise of like you know and
perhaps different competing worldviews
right and so there's like this tension
right and and but that tension can be
you know you can think of it as
generative tension that it actually
creates something and you and you go you
know form rises around it and then you
get to a certain point and then all of a
sudden and then you go back into the
null space I haven't really thought this
out very much it's just it's just
something that's like kind of you know
I've been kind of concept I've been I've
been exploring but you know one more I
can remember what a last thing I wanted
to bring up last thing I can't remember
probably remember in two seconds Jared
you want to go yeah well I just want to
like kind of flesh out this this liminal
versus generative tension dynamic and
kind of I guess using another metaphor
that I think is use a lot when it comes
to it's like very readily available with
politics in the sense that we kind of
have to we have a conservative in a
liberal perspective and you know ideally
the way that society should be working
is that we're kind of the traditional
perspective is kind of informing us from
what we've learned from the past and
what what works this progressive is
trying to understand how we need to
change and kind of reach into operating
in new new levels and when things are
working well their income they're there
they're in generative tension there
a dialogue something more than the then
each of them is arising out of the the
tension between the two and I think I
like the metaphor of of magnets here
right so the closer they get all of a
sudden we get this this this energetic
exchange that happens but if they're too
far away it vanishes and then there's no
longer anything that's being generative
in addition so they're just kind of both
isolated and so to Jason's point right
here right is like in order for us to
get that generator attention to realized
somebody has to occupy this liminal
space in between and kind of allow them
to see and get closer to each other
for something to arise out of that the
dynamic I don't that's the metaphor
that's coming up as you're you're
speaking about an adjacent generation
before I hand it over to the group you
have any uh closing thoughts or opening
one more thought it's a little bit
unrelated but it's just one more angle
that I've been thinking so so up until
now we've had you know we've had
different kinds of sessions we've had a
session where you know we you know we
had an inquiry about what kind of
internal cognitive dissonance or you
know what kind of warring ideas are
happening within yourself right and we
had a whole session where you know
people were able to express you know
this kind of tension within themselves
or you can you can say it's kind of an
internalization of the of the warring
ideologies or ideas or memes in the
outside world but sometimes we're also
torn apart or split right and me like
the medic mediation kind of works on
many levels and works within ourselves
and works outside and it's kind of a
contemplator practice to be a memetic
mediator my point of view is because
we're having to internalize these as
dissonance and and work with it
ourselves right and so I'm wondering but
you know so we've had these different
kinds of sessions and now we're kind of
having a session where we're getting a
little more meta and kind of talking
about it
you know where's last week Jared you
know I know I wasn't there but I know
they had a conversation like with a
specific issue with a couple people and
like
you know with these different angles on
it and that was a very different thing
the time before that and I don't have
any meta thing but I like this idea of
kind of rotating modes where we have
like you know a mode we're talking about
kind of object level you know memes and
mimetic tribes or whatever and then you
know another session where we're having
more internal contemplative type of
conversation and then you know maybe
every third or fourth time we had kind
of a meta conversation because how is
this going you know what needs to change
right but we only have the meta kind of
conversation like every third or fourth
time right cuz we don't want to be meta
because that you want to get into it as
well so that's that's my next thought
yeah yeah and it's to plug our upcoming
papers at the side view so you know what
you're just discussing about kind of
mediating the sort of personalities the
internal psychodynamic aspect that I
think that was what you're writing about
and the side view partly and then yeah
just as a good like you and I were
originally trying to co-write a paper
and we couldn't mediate between each so
he just kind of wrote our own papers but
that felt like even though there was
maybe some annoyances that we were
flying around but I think that we ended
up in right relationship there because I
think kind of papers were needed for
that so I think that's coming out and at
this Adam Roberts side view in next week
I think so I'm gonna open up two hundred
peer can I just add one little quick
thing I'm always trying to get some
visual metaphor here because it seems to
help my my brain but to Jason's point
yeah like the project here is largely to
like kind of understand what this to
understand what this minim attic
mediation is because we don't we don't
really know this is a process of
figuring it out in a lot of ways I see
kind of like building putting a puzzle
together and building a puzzle kind of
requires us to spend time like you know
very very specifically and narrowly
focusing on the shape of each individual
piece and how they fit together
the color of it you know it has a lot of
different dynamics and then other times
to Jason's point like the meta
conversations it's kind of us like
taking a step back and looking at
whole picture and being like all right
now where are the gaps how is this
connecting over here you know what you
know what what areas are more or less
developed where should we concentrate on
here
so yeah the meta level is is you know
very kind of abroad as brought up as
perspective as we can employ to figure
out then where to go get back to putting
piece by piece together yeah in my whole
sense there is that you know this is a
memetic mediation trying to find itself
right now collectively and maybe the
three of us are just like one page ahead
of some people but like we're not that
far ahead we're not epistemic
authorities of this this thing and I
think there's a discovery of what it is
and what it could be and how to do it so
if anybody I will trust everyone can
just unmute themselves will trust you to
discern mint if you want to like
disagree with us we accept your
propositional violence and we will model
mimetic mediation live if you have any
practical ideas of what what sessions
can be borne out of this we're open to
hear that or if anything just came alive
so the floor is yours sure care what the
role of a mediator is or how I think a
mediator should be sure alright sorry
I'm a bit nervous you know it's the
first time talking in front of such big
crowd and I'm happy that you're all here
so I'll go ahead and get started then I
think that a mediator has like a really
hard job to be able to stand outside of
the conflict that may happen and to be
able to just emotionally distance
yourself from the crew so it's generally
that you're more likely to be attracted
to these emotions and so we have to be
in the sort of way disciplined to make
sure that do not let ourselves become
bias and so when I think of like really
tough decision makers it generally has
to be in a position where the calm
unethical to do those choices so for
example here a big political player you
might have to take policies between
immigration and what I'm saying here is
that sometimes those people are forced
into situations and they have to be
disciplined in their motions in order to
make what anything is a sensible or
choice and will never ever uncover a
full perspective and knowledge of all
these choices but the only thing in ever
or is to do our best in those positions
and and that's what I think why is are
important and we take someone that can
be just about any ideology but also
disciplined enough to refuse it if
necessary so yeah that's my take on it
and thank you
anybody else want to respond to that or
we're coming with a different angle
yeah and just feel popcorn style just
jump in will be awkwardly silent waiting
yeah I think you know I'm very
interested in each of what you were
saying about this idea of dipping in and
I imagined you are drawing a kind of
two-dimensional axis without sense and
propositions and you know what's
happening on that access for you know
everybody in dialogue you know as we're
speaking but one of the questions that
came up for me was in pneumatic
mediation you know what where is this
mediation actually is it sort of
happening you know within bodies between
bodies within concepts or ideas or
between concepts or ideas and and what
is the role of the tribe here and and
how do we face conflict and do conflict
and you know what does it mean to look
between tribes to conflict you know in
preference to looking sort of within
tribes for conflict and in response to
what the last speaker was saying this
idea of standing outside I think is very
tricky you know what might an outside
space be you know in mimetic mediation
is difficult to imagine there's
something that's alive like those are
great questions I don't know the answers
to it but so my kind of conception of
the metagame
is there's like you know the biosphere
or the language that's being spoken
there like or with our bodies is like
that primal ape and then the the
emotive sphere that's for the language
of emotions and felt sensor being spoken
and then the the noosphere that's the
realm of memes and propositions are
being spoken and I think you have to
have fluency in each one of those
languages in order to speak to people
really well and so yeah that's that's
just sort of like a skill set I think
needs to be developed for not just a
medic mediator but a meta gamer in
general and I think your questions are
excellent I would cease
here I've bit of an I guess outlying
position on mediation where it takes
place when we see it and you know I've
kind of publicly said I think even on
our last conversation I don't really
like mediation because it I don't like
it as a word I think it's provocative
and that's why you're all here but I
think of it more as a orientation than a
result and you know if when I see the
most movement happening it seems to be
long-term all right so I guess what I'm
saying is if we can find ourselves in
all the conversations that we have
personal familial online on Twitter with
your best friend whatever it is of kind
of a dot of making an effort to
understand multiple perspectives and not
trying to prove or disprove them you
know as your core motivation and I think
mediation happens wherever you go
and maybe that word never comes up and
probably you know I actually think of it
probably it's it's most effective if the
you know if we for example if we were to
have some of the the famous disagreeing
intellectuals of the stoah to come on
here on the mediation campfire I think
it would actually be like that end of
that conversation is likely to have not
a ton of movement whereas if we were to
just orient it as a campfire for
relation or something like that you know
but the campfire here is is pointing to
the warmth though so yeah I don't know I
I see this is a long game and an
orientation of not being pro ideology or
or or you know pushing your perspective
hardcore and instead kind of finding
ourselves often in the space in between
the tribes and when that happens or in
you know mediation is kind of a an
emergent result in a long term and one
other kind of little note here too just
that attack on sorry I don't want to
take you much time but
is this this question of understanding
the perspectives of people and I think
that it is valuable to understand both
the perspectives because we can kind of
see common mistakes or misconceptions or
semantics arguments as they arise but I
also think that that's not always
required and another orientation can be
you know in a lot of ways is very
helpful is to be just the genuinely
inquisitively curious person you know
I'm sure kids have doing a lot of
mediation for their parents because they
have no idea what's going on and they
ask simple questions and they're
genuinely interested in understanding
the the answers as opposed to having an
agenda about one way or the other so
yeah I think you know when in doubt if
surprising how much work can be done
from coming from a place of genuine
curiosity and little agenda just a few
thoughts throughout there Richard
Bartlett mentioned a while back that you
mentioned the term medic diplomat and I
actually I'm being honest in the way a
mediation and diplomat is being used I
see myself more as trying to be a medic
diplomat and then a mediator because a
mediator has you know a specific
structure you know usually you have like
the you know a couple parties and a
third party like a mediating between two
people and that's actually not like that
like for me that's that's part of it but
kind of going what Jared said it you
know for me it's really a lot of its
informal it's just relationship building
with with people who think differently
than me and you know perhaps you know
and that can be you know if if it's too
difficult to build a relationship based
on ideas it can be just based on shared
aesthetics taste right shared love with
baseball or you know shared love of you
know listening to Bob Dylan or something
right and you know and eventually when
things flare up and there's just this
general genuine misunderstanding between
groups of people you know you're you
know if you're in a position where you
have relationships with people on both
of those sides you can kind of help
transmit information back and forth with
more signal than would have been
otherwise so kind of like this
connective tissue and so you can kind of
you know you
you helped to facilitate collective
intelligence is I guess the way I think
about it there was one of the vision one
of the metaphors that comes to mind for
me visual metaphors that comes to mind
for me is like is a bridge but also
Jared as you were talking it was more of
the word glue kept coming into mind and
being that you know Peter like he said
the space in between tribes but it's
being able to you know I have I know
that I have an ability to detect like
changes in volumes or tones of voice in
a very subtle way and in language and
can see things ratcheting up and will
and have in my life been known to stop
something in order to prevent it from
escalating any further and so being so
but but also like being able to be you
know in the I think I've always been the
type of person that will take the
opposite of if somebody takes a strong
position even if I in general agree with
them will automatically take like the
opposite perspective just because
there's this just deep desire in me for
balance and so so Jason I I liked the
word diplomat but there's also yeah this
you know sense of needing this balance
that comes when someone takes a strong
position and wanting to immediately like
even if I even if I don't agree with the
opposing position will try and present
the argument of the opposing position
just because I like I can't have that
that imbalance and so and I see a couple
of other people saying that they do the
same thing so that's yeah that's a
similar thing and and so but being able
to or and one of the thoughts that came
to my Peter you referenced like the
three different levels and like I'm very
comfortable in the emotional level like
that
I know in backwards and forwards and
inside-out but when it comes to more of
the ideas and being able to articulate
those on a kind of a faster rate my
brain just kind of goes it and so like
having a way to practice that piece of
it you know is it was something that was
coming to mind was like being able to
practice at those various levels and and
kind of getting a clear like I like I
have a some sense of what you what you
meant but getting a clearer idea of each
of those levels I would that would be
really helpful
yeah maybe I've been reading a little
bit about in my journals but so the the
biosphere was sort of like the
interactions that primal miss Jared and
myself we were sort of dipped our or
dipped into the pickup artist scene and
then they sort of leveraged evolutionary
biology in order to attract women but
and I'm also a trainer at Dale Carnegie
Training and Jonathan hight he called
Dale Carnegie sort of the elephant
whisperer and he used the metaphor of
the elephant the rider like system one
system two and you got to talk to the
elephant you don't talk to the rider if
you can talk to the elephant then you
can really make friends and influence
people so that's sort of like that kind
of that primal level that's the sort of
language that can be spoken that social
skills books anything you can learn from
and then the other level is the level of
the motor sphere like what you were sort
of like have a natural talent and
probably like where you just feel people
like when things heat up things heat up
in your body right and then sort of like
you know you address that and and I can
feel people's words right and when I
zone out when everyone the word feels
the same it feels disembodied so that's
sort of like the if you can speak at
that language then it's like you can
kind of ignore some of the the red
herrings in the propositional realm and
then really get at the heart what the
person is trying to say and this is sort
of what Jordan holiday and I smoked a
burger called the Omega roll just really
really listen and then the other ones
that run with the proposition and then
someone said what about objective truth
that's sort of like in that realm like
is there an objective truth lift can we
level set on it and this is where things
get really messy though because if
anyone read my paper in the culture with
that spreadsheet there's a lot of people
that have different reality tiles that
are flying around and if you can get
really skilled at being meta and Jason
and I were talking about this in one of
our letter exchanges I think I called
the perspectival pigeon ISM it's like
you can kind of take mental models from
each one of these tribes create your own
sort of respect type of language and use
the right model for the right person at
the right time so if you're coming with
someone who has a social justice
proclivity you can use hierarchy or
something like that if you're coming
someone with a reactionary you can use
nan and then you can kind of speak to
them and relate to them on that level so
that's sort of like what I understand is
the metagame and I don't know no
training out there for it so maybe we'll
invent one here at the stoah but that's
sort of
at the edge of my thinking and above the
last sentence you said Peter about
training weight before and I think would
be probably like almost like to bring
things from here on to the real world
almost kind of like homework our
missions reminded kind of like in Fight
Club where they got that envelope sort
of like you have to go in to find
something like that where it be kind of
something that people here who would be
interested in the best kind of an
invitation try to do like this one thing
and in the field of memory Asian and
then you can kind of come back and like
for your field observations like what
did you see what did not work probably
the first couple of times or what was
too easy here and I wondered that could
kind of also create internal training
program for everybody's interested to
give people ideas some sort of
accountability and also kind of create
the knowledge base to develop this
yeah like that um hello everybody thank
you for all the effort and energy
everyone's put in so far my name is Ben
and I want to be mindful first of all
the first stoic session I attended was
building the stoah and the mediator of
that session travis warned against
bringing a cathedral and recommended
bringing a brick and that's something
that I may not be doing here and I think
David who's in attendance we I brought
this up and actually Peter I've
mentioned a project to you and a DM on
Twitter about a way sort of my demonic
reaction to reading the cultural war
paper I immediately went out and bought
the URL called reality museum org and I
guess this is sort of linked somewhat to
Jordan Hall's idea of a news channel um
but it also relies on a a visual
metaphor sort of thinking of
perspectives as frameworks and I just
had this vision for creating a website
in which a essentially a museum was was
built off of set of reality tunnels
their gallery spaces and I should say -
on to Jason's point about my own biases
I'm a visual person I come from the Art
and Design background so I always
gravitate this way but I've been really
wanting to get some momentum under this
idea and I ironically picked a
collaborator who at we ultimately
couldn't mediate between our two
different sort of outlooks on the world
but um anyhow I just it's very helpful
for me - thinking in a very sort of
cohesive visual metaphor and this one
the role of the mediator becomes more
like a docent so a volunteer
who's familiar with all the galleries in
the museum and doesn't necessarily have
to like the frameworks in one gallery
but should know all these galleries are
here and this is how other people see
the world and anyhow I just wanted to to
share and mostly to to say thank you to
Peter and Jared and Jason and everyone
else I found I found I think that's
intriguing one one thing that comes up
for me is a from my perspective I don't
think anybody would ever be able to
understand enough you know the whole
mimetic landscape like it so if you if
you were to have something to develop
them like that seems like you need a lot
of collaborators from people from
different backgrounds to help curate and
that's probably we had in mind anyway
right because I don't think you know me
it's like mimetic mediators is like we
kind of have to lock arms and try and
cover the whole space and many of us are
gonna come from you know way more on the
right maybe more on the anarchist or the
you know from the left or you know you
know all over the place and work you
know each of us it has probably a
special set of skills mediating between
certain kind of meta clusters but I
don't at least I can you know I can't
even imagine trying to cover all of them
understanding them well enough to like
like I couldn't go into queueing on like
there's no freaking way like I would try
and do that but you know but if somebody
else can and then I can mediate with
them it's like there's these multiple
levels where the mediators media with
each other and but then they all cover
you know different different parts of
the map but then they come back together
and hash out any any remaining issues
among themselves yeah I don't know if
that was helpful or if benefits if that
was relevant to your idea absolutely
it's for more than I could chew by
myself but yeah thank you
something else that is coming up also
from the museum idea and also from
before the whole mediation and concept
is kind of the role of not the mediator
who's outside the group but the person
is inside the group which is I think
that pretty much everybody has some sort
of identity to a certain extent um there
was an ideology or some of the mimetic
tribe and I wonder if there could be
better
mediation not being a third party of
being one of the two people in a
two-party rule we're coming as
representative I don't even have a
stronger effect where someone would say
oh I am a neo reactionary I want a
monarchy and and from that position I
want to talk to somebody who is I don't
know help said that would be I guess the
Democrat I don't know I don't even know
- so anyone's a democracy but I want I
wouldn't have that would that would be
more powerful than being a third party
well I think we're all insiders in some
in some mimetic clusters right like we
all that's that relates back to you know
putting our biases on our sleeves is
because we are all coming from a place
and and that's perhaps where we can be
the most effective is if we can see our
own biases and know the third biases but
we can also represent that perspective
in a way that's constructive you know
when engaging another perspective so I
got that question maybe for Jason bills
for the group about the bias is like
putting it on your sleeve and stuff like
that I'm becoming more bold in my
writing just kind of like speaking my
truth but I'm speaking in such a way
where you know I could be disabused of
the propositions if presented with a
good argument but like you know I'm
talking about like masculine and
feminine type stuff and at times even
though I don't consider myself a
conservative its might sound like it to
some and so there's like a sensitivity
of getting cancelled for myself if I'm
too bold with
my thoughts out there because it's like
if you just take one snippet of what I
said propositional e and then without
the context of the whole letter or even
that context of the spirit of how I'm
writing and then you almost fossilized
me as sort of like this disembodied
proposition that's wrong and evil so I
haven't figured out how to be a right
relationship with that but I'm curious
what you think about that how does a
medic mediator sort of play chess with
canceled culture is it's the Jim Jason
and in the whole group I would say very
skillfully I think I think one of the
the talents that can be developed as a
mediator is is learning learning how to
speak truth in a way that avoids the the
really obvious triggers that will get
you canceled of course you know a lot of
people know that now you know I I know
that's for example you know a lot of
knee reactionaries on Twitter are very
good at speaking in code right you're
getting their truths across to each
other and to some on the app you know
without getting cancelled you know and
so but but at the same time you know
that also might feel limiting as well
like oh I have to I have to think about
which word I'm gonna use because this
one is unnecessarily triggering but
there also might be case where it
doesn't matter like the truth you want
to express
there's no papering over it like it's
gonna it's gonna trigger people as well
and that and in that case that's you
know you know that it might there might
be a time in a place where you have to
take that risk and there's there's no
there's no way to to avoid the
unnecessary triggers I don't know I'm
just wondering if
multiple perspectives and multiple
voices and thinking about you know it's
their attention between sort of really
wanting to find you know one voice and
what it's like to really try and follow
a particular singular thread compared to
you know inviting you know other voices
other perspectives into the conversation
so jump in um like I think that would be
really good opportunity for anyone who
hasn't like spoken yet we have about ten
minutes so if anyone hasn't spoken yet
and wants to answer that question to
share their thoughts feel free to do so
could you rephrase it I'm Ben I'm a
little I'm a little confused exactly
what you're asking could you rephrase it
well maybe some of the some of the ideas
or even skills or activities that have
been presented I've been around the idea
for example of a single tension and so
in a sense it might be easier to bring
in a second and a third and a fourth
tension where the focus is on one so you
know what's it what's it made maybe it
makes more sense to have a single focus
that's coming again a kind of
collaboration of a few different people
airing our own biases right like really
fundamentally this is like admitting
that none of us are not everyone of us
is a hypocrite
right we hold we have a ton of different
beliefs identifications and the closer
we look at them we realized that they a
lot of intersections where they does
they're in a disagreement with each
other and so this is kind of pointing to
the fact
but there's holes in our story and one
of the simplest practices here is like
is being aware of that I mean be like
really like well how do out what what
are some of the areas that that don't
agree from from my of my own beliefs and
things like that and that can kind of
start to highlight not only the space in
between the concepts but the space that
permeates all of the concepts too and
both of these things kind of give you a
little bit more release and a little bit
less capture and kind of constriction
around the ideas and Bend to your point
I think this is really important to
think of when we're in a mediation
perspective and and and I like the the
plurality role right like I'm gonna
confuse people by using conservative
language to describe a liberal or a
progressive ideal that with words that
would normally trigger them so they're
you know all of a sudden they're like
whoa like this is the this is like an
idea that's pulling in like five
different conflicting things and it
makes me uncomfortable and and and kind
of a little ungrounded maybe looking
around to try and figure out what's
going on into Kyra's point to like often
we know this is devil's advocate
sometimes we can think of it as like
everything has an opposite but I think
it's even more multi-dimensional or than
that you know if a concept is kind of
some sort of each one has its own shape
any anywhere around and this is a 3d
shape - it's not not just a circle but
you know any elements around the entire
ideal the complex of ideas that hold it
together can be explored challenged
questioned and and one of the things
that I find the most useful to get to
Google to start loosening some of their
grip on ideology is to like look for the
places that are less clear for them and
then all the sudden to be coming up this
idea that they had a solid idea of what
something was starts to be challenged a
little bit when we try and understand
where the boundary is we really look
closely and see that's like well you're
not quite there
so yeah this isn't you know ambiguity
nebulosity kind of open this like these
are all all things you know this is
where meeting
arises from and the rigidity of patterns
and ideas that we have captured is what
we're trying to you know to kind of
break those apart and let them relate
and see each other we you know there's a
million ways to kind of introduce a
little bit of space and it comes in a
lot of flavors but unfortunately this is
an uncomfortable process yeah just just
a few thoughts to kind of go in here and
make things a little bit more complex
abstract sorry can I speak to softest
sure yeah so I feed also it sim as
written for this question of bin and
what I was trying to particularly to
earlier like last week we had this
example of mediation between about
Israel and so I think in to have a
relationship to truth as actually we all
have a relationship to truth in all ways
we could not have a conversation without
having some sort of relationship and so
I think it's not just about biases it
also about something outside of
ourselves like yeah so for Sam Israel so
we need to be able to talk about like
the history and so that can be different
sides to it but still as a grounding
like say what happened in 1970 or 1980
or who did what my kids so yeah so there
can be different perspectives
interpretations and even facts can be
disagreed upon but still I think there's
this level of what the content is like I
think content is for me the best word
that we need to have a relationship and
and how to have a relationship with but
conscience is also part of mediation and
also so yeah if it's something you don't
know so much about then you would have a
different relationship than if you're an
expert like if you're an expert in
Israel history then you could have a
different mediation than if you were not
known as one in this area
thank you so um we got three minutes
left so if one person one person has
closed your thoughts anyone does it all
make some closing announcements Jason or
Jared if you guys want to you guys have
anything
I mean mind is trying to think of a way
to summarize and you know in a way that
kind of leads us directly forward
grasping but it's not finding anything
maybe that's okay I feel like a lot of
different ideas are kind of floating
around and we might need a few or more
of these sessions to or some something
to start to cohere in terms of you know
either more of a formalized training is
I think someone recommended or you know
perhaps some actual using the space for
actual mediation but yeah I guess I
guess it's still a little bit liminal
for me right so so I have a practical
idea that we can throw it there and I'll
say what I liked and didn't like about
the session what I liked about the
session was I don't often talk about at
the edge of my thinking aloud so that
was a good opportunity and then like I
like hearing Jason and Jared to think I
didn't like about it it's so Jason Jared
and myself we have the proclivity to
masturbate about the meta okay it just
felt like we were masturbating in front
of you all for a little bit and you know
it's okay but as a facilitator in the
space of the story I want this to be
about us the collective intelligence not
about what this perceived epistemic
Authority we are so that can be totally
missed reading that whole situation
people and then I felt that but that's
sort of what I'm leaving with I'd like
you don't like about it
meta modern masturbation can I don't
know okay there's a secret handshake for
it I don't know if you want to learn
that right now so an idea so we have a
slack group I'm a medic mediator slack
group and David just created a mediation
campfire a channel on it so if someone
could maybe I don't know who has a link
to that some of the pose
that link in the chat box you her to
join it and let's just spit ball
throughout the week about what we can do
here because it's just me and Jason
Jared just come kind of coming up with
it ourselves but we can collectively
come up with an idea and just run with
it and we're as you can tell from the
previous sessions were really really
open to experiment with this so that
being said Jason Jared you have any
closing thoughts before I make
announcements to about coming events at
the store mm-hmm no I think if getting
some more dialogue going throughout the
week you know in this channel I think
would be good so we can kind of flesh
out some of these ideas that people have
been putting out and we've you know we
haven't had we haven't had the time to
really you know carefully go through
each one so I think if people want to
join that I think that would be a really
good way to you know yep one quick kind
of note on the bias discussion well I
think bias is a very real thing and it's
a good lens to use when we're trying to
understand how people make decisions I
think from the mediation toolkit I don't
find it super valuable and and and
actually prefer just perspective you
know this is kind of a radical
relativism but due to utility rather
than any kind of ultimate to truth and
and yeah if we're genuinely interacting
with people in a in a from a place of
just trying to understand everybody's
perspectives
I forget actually it's far more fruitful
rather than kind of bringing in the
negative connotation of who's biases are
gonna cause problems so just a little
thought on that and then last thing as
we're closing Peter I know we did
mention the the play play acting role
and and I love Ben you know Benjamin
saying that if anyone wanted to be like
hey I'm I'm this somebody want to argue
against it yeah like I'm very much I'm
open to triggering anybody that would
like to be triggered so you know
invitations are out there and yeah so if
there's a perspective I might be able to
even do it ignorantly those are some of
the most triggering ones that you can
find so
if anyone wants to see me be combative
I'll be I'll be game to jump into those
waters we can discuss it in the mediate
mediation Channel quick question about
the slack channel what um channel in the
slack room did you want the idea isn't
so a David the created one called
mediation campfire or he has their will
and you just have to like there's TV
there's already one now there's a second
one
okay so join one of them join the one
that's most popular go from there we'll
figure that great and if you can't
figure out how to join this lock you
know Jason jeered and myself and I heart
to find his message us somewhere and
then we'll get you on it so thanks
everyone for coming
I'll just make some upcoming
announcements so how do these haven't
been posted yet I just want to tell the
lineup for next week I'm so excited so
we have a sore you from the monastic
Academy the head teacher there he's
coming on Monday talking about monastic
conversations we have a Thomas workman
bjrkman the guy who actually coined the
meta-crisis he's like the main funder of
emerge and rebel is dumb he's coming in
on Tuesday Michael Brooks also is coming
on Tuesday from the Michael Brooks show
Brad Blanton that popular self-help
author called from radical honesty nor
Bateson's coming on wednesday both
bradden or on wednesday and Greg
Hendricks and then Justin Murphy are on
Thursday and then the food's next week
so and that's an addition to all the
wisdom Jim so we got a packed lineup is
gonna be dope I'm going to post it
tonight and then tonight we have if you
want something more fun and light we
have an oxytocin party at 8:00 p.m.
Eastern Time with the beautiful ray of
Sun and we're just gonna chill in relax
so yeah join us and that we can RSVP on
that one though that's that's yay
alright everyone thanks so much it's
been a pleasure as always be well and
Jason Geordi I'd like a couple minutes
just deeply